<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Golang on Bits, Rhymes and Life</title>
    <link>http://blog.nocdib.com/tags/golang/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Golang on Bits, Rhymes and Life</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://blog.nocdib.com/tags/golang/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Throwback Thursday: Crucial Conflict - Hay / Scummy</title>
      <link>http://blog.nocdib.com/Throwback-Thursday-Crucial-Conflict-Hay-Scummy/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Aug 2016 22:27:47 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.nocdib.com/Throwback-Thursday-Crucial-Conflict-Hay-Scummy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Throwback Thursday: Crucial Conflict: Hay / Scummy&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/3Fg2NRCB9Sc&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/xArkAYPkkp8&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
Back in 1996 I remember seeing a promo video (commercial) on &lt;a href=&#34;https://youtu.be/fEs8LanCuKw?list=RDSCf4203RnLM&#34;&gt;The Box&lt;/a&gt;, a now defunct music video channel, for a group called Crucial Conflict. To paraphrase the tagline, &amp;ldquo;The sun rises in the east and sets in the west but its highest point is in the middle.&amp;rdquo; Those words were voiced over video footage of a horse-drawn carriage riding through the hood. Soon, I saw the video for &amp;ldquo;Hay&amp;rdquo; with the country-western-inspired imagery of barnyards, cowboys, leather and denim overalls offset by the urban imagery of Black men with braided hair rapping about &amp;ldquo;smoking on hay in the middle of the barn.&amp;rdquo; The description may seem ridiculous, especially by today&amp;rsquo;s standards of what good rap music is, but they pulled it off well.
&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
Crucial Conflict emerged from Chicago at a time when the R&amp;amp;B infused raps about street life were winding down and the violent, gang-related lyrics of drill music had yet to come. They had a good mix of solid lyricism and unique style with their &amp;ldquo;rodeo rap.&amp;rdquo; Instead of following the quick-tongue style that was popularized in their region they were similar to Three Six Mafia in delivery and Lil&amp;rsquo; Jon&amp;rsquo;s crunk music for the party factor. I remember their debut album &amp;ldquo;The Final Tic&amp;rdquo; selling Gold at some point and when I started high school later that year &amp;ldquo;Hay&amp;rdquo; was playing in portable stereos once class let out for the day.
&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
They had fallen off of my radar for a couple of years until I saw a video for &amp;ldquo;Scummy,&amp;rdquo; the lead single from a follow-up album titled &amp;ldquo;Good Side Bad Side&amp;rdquo;. True to their original form they were back with the hard-hitting rodeo rap that made you subconsciously nod your head. I heard them featured on a song with R. Kelly but aside from that they never made it big, which is sad because I consider them to be the most innovative rap outfit from Chicago in the 90&amp;rsquo;s. I recently revisited their music on Spotify and was enthused to see a Crucial Conflict release from this year only to find out that it was a heavy metal group using the name. Maybe the group has long since called it quits but for at least a brief period of time they made their mark on rap music.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Best Golang Tutorial Around</title>
      <link>http://blog.nocdib.com/The-best-golang-tutorial-around/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Mar 2016 13:21:51 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.nocdib.com/The-best-golang-tutorial-around/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;TL;DR: Read &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.golangbootcamp.com/book&#34; target=&#34;_new&#34;&gt;this tutorial&lt;/a&gt; and watch &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.udemy.com/learn-how-to-code/learn/v4/content&#34; target=&#34;_new&#34;&gt;these videos&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Golang, also known as Go, has been gaining traction in recent years as a mainstream programming language, particularly in the space of web services. At a time when dynamically-typed, interpreted languages like Python and Ruby are dominating that arena while the frameworks that are built with them are handling front-end content or REST API calls I found it interesting that a statically-typed, compiled language had a growing buzz around it. Back in Spring 2012, after I had just ended a job that made heavy use of Erlang I remember my cousin&amp;rsquo;s husband mentioning his interest in learning Go. Having just dealt with a niche language like Erlang&amp;ndash;which I found to be unpleasant&amp;ndash;I wasn&amp;rsquo;t interested in even hearing about another programming language that hadn&amp;rsquo;t been widely adopted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the middle of 2014 &lt;a href=&#34;http://nickmanning.net/&#34; target=&#34;_new&#34;&gt;Nick Manning&lt;/a&gt; started the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/nycgolang/&#34; target=&#34;_new&#34;&gt;Golang NYC meetup group&lt;/a&gt; and I began attending since I already knew him from the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/nycneo4j/&#34; target=&#34;_new&#34;&gt;NYC Neo4j meetup group&lt;/a&gt;. Hearing the testimonials of Go converts piqued my interest but one meeting in particular made me want to try the language for myself. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bjornroche.com/&#34; target=&#34;_new&#34;&gt;Bjorn Roche&lt;/a&gt; gave a presentation about using the &lt;a href=&#34;https://revel.github.io/&#34; target=&#34;_new&#34;&gt;Revel web framework&lt;/a&gt; to power the backend of the mobile app &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.shimmeo.com/&#34; target=&#34;_new&#34;&gt;Shimmeo&lt;/a&gt;. During the presentation he compared Revel to the Java/Scala web framework &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.playframework.com&#34; target=&#34;_new&#34;&gt;Play&lt;/a&gt;. I had a strong interest in Play and was about to use it on my own personal project but after hearing that there was a Go equivalent I was convinced to give Go and Revel a try. Nothing helps you learn a new language better than actually implementing something with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first step was to learn Go. I&amp;rsquo;m pretty particular with my learning materials and I&amp;rsquo;m just not the type who becomes proficient from online documentation and web searches alone. Finding the right introductory material wasn&amp;rsquo;t easy since there was a dearth of tutorials and well-written, published books on Go. I had found one e-book, whose name I will not mention, but I found its explanation and the progression of material to be deficient. By chance I had stumbled upon one of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/user/toddmcleod&#34; target=&#34;_new&#34;&gt;Todd Mcleod&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a&gt; YouTube videos and left a comment. He quickly responded and suggested that I take a look at a new Golang video course that he recently published on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.udemy.com/learn-how-to-code/learn/v4/content&#34; target=&#34;_new&#34;&gt;Udemy&lt;/a&gt;. I bought access to the videos for a nominal fee and it was the best investment in programming-related material that I have ever made. Simply put, if you have prior computer programming experience there is no way that you couldn&amp;rsquo;t become proficient with Go by the end of the course. While doing the course I had also come across Matt Aimonetti&amp;rsquo;s e-book &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.golangbootcamp.com/book&#34; target=&#34;_new&#34;&gt;Go Bootcamp&lt;/a&gt; and noticed that Todd McLeod&amp;rsquo;s course actually elaborated on many of those examples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are interested in learning Go and are looking for a tutorial that blends brevity with comprehensiveness then I suggest reading &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.golangbootcamp.com/book&#34; target=&#34;_new&#34;&gt;Go Bootcamp&lt;/a&gt;. If you need greater depth then look at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.udemy.com/learn-how-to-code/learn/v4/content&#34; target=&#34;_new&#34;&gt;Todd&amp;rsquo;s video course on Udemy&lt;/a&gt;. After tackling the language with these resources I actually found it better to create my own REST API without using a framework. Go is a powerful language that allows you to do just that without a lot of overhead.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>