<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Life on Bits, Rhymes and Life</title>
    <link>http://blog.nocdib.com/tags/life/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Life on Bits, Rhymes and Life</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 11 Apr 2016 13:32:10 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://blog.nocdib.com/tags/life/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Learning How To Learn Part 1: Choosing The Proper Resources</title>
      <link>http://blog.nocdib.com/Learning-How-To-Learn-Part-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Apr 2016 13:32:10 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.nocdib.com/Learning-How-To-Learn-Part-1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;For most of my life I had conflated the word &amp;ldquo;learn&amp;rdquo; with the word &amp;ldquo;memorize.&amp;rdquo; Sadly, I think that the American education system is responsible for this because, for as long as I could remember, memorizing information was given precedence over actually understanding what was taught. The only subject that defied this convention was Mathematics which also happened to be the subject I liked the least. The problem with only memorizing atomic facts of information is that while you may be able to recall information accurately enough to get the correct answer on a test you overlook the importance of personally interpreting the information and making connections with other bits of information. The more I work with graph databases (Neo4j in particular) is the more I see the real-life applications of connected information, data.&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
&amp;ldquo;Information&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;data&amp;rdquo; are two more words that are often wrongfully used synonymously but I don&amp;rsquo;t intend to go into detail on commonly misused English words. When it comes to learning I am actually still &lt;i&gt;&lt;u&gt;learning&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/i&gt; how to do it in the best way for myself. I compare it to any skill where there are a core set of basic principles that the individual develops their own personal style from. Right now, I&amp;rsquo;m refining my personal style of learning to achieve the result of gaining understanding, efficiently.&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
Terms like &amp;ldquo;visual learner&amp;rdquo; have crept into the American scholastic vocabulary over the last decade but they didn&amp;rsquo;t exist when I was going to school. I&amp;rsquo;ve come to see that although I can function well with traditional learning methods I actually learn quicker with aided instruction. In other words, I can read material and teach myself something, however, I progress more quickly through visually-aided learning. In an age where streaming online video is pervasive I&amp;rsquo;m sure this style of learning has helped many more folks other than myself. Something about didactic engagement, whether it&amp;rsquo;s real-time or asynchronous, resonates well with me but I realize that the method of teaching is only as effective as the resource conveying the information.&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
Last year I paid for &lt;a href=&#34;https://fedora.bitfountain.io/courses/android&#34;&gt;a self-paced online course&lt;/a&gt; that taught Android development. I had never found a book on the subject that worked well with me nor had I found any of the online tutorials, even ones from Google, helpful past the initial stages. As a result, I had for a long time dismissed Android development as something that was hard to learn and not worth my time. Apple iOS development, on the other hand, had a variety of written resources that were easier for me to understand and become quickly productive with. When I started the Android course it was informative and I thought I was progressing well but several hours into it I came to realize that it had gone from explaining concepts to basically saying &amp;ldquo;enter this code to see this happen.&amp;rdquo; At the beginning I was taking notes but for several of the videos I hadn&amp;rsquo;t taken a single note because I hadn&amp;rsquo;t learned anything. You can tell anyone how to enter some code and run a command to make the computer display &amp;ldquo;hello, world&amp;rdquo; but if you don&amp;rsquo;t explain the mechanics behind what is going on then the student hasn&amp;rsquo;t learned why what they are doing provides the end result. The course, like most resources on computer programming ended up being like this:&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://blog.nocdib.com/blog_images/owl.jpg&#34;&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
Choosing resources that compliment your style of learning is crucial. Not everything will work for everyone. I can&amp;rsquo;t say that the course wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be beneficial to anyone because someone could compensate for the lack of explanation with their own research and gain understanding that way but I simply don&amp;rsquo;t have the time to be presented with information that I have to research just to understand it. I require a resource that explains the what and the why in enough detail so that I can apply it independently and then do any requisite research, if necessary. This is why there are scores of books written on any given subject. Whether it&amp;rsquo;s teaching calculus, basket-weaving, origami, etc. the intention of any instructional text is the same but each one may not work the same way with everyone&amp;rsquo;s style of learning and level of understanding. I used to wonder why many major book stores often include cafes where you could read books before buying them and even had lenient refund policies where you could return a book within a timeframe that you could actually finish reading it. Now I know why. Auditing your resources is important. Committing to anything for the purpose of learning should be treated like an interpersonal relationship but with an inanimate object. When you find something you like you should get to know it and see if it could be right for you. If there is strong potential that it will give you what you need then you could fully commit to it but if it doesn&amp;rsquo;t meet your expectations it&amp;rsquo;s best to end things quickly so as not to waste your time. Ultimately, the relationship you have with learning is one that you have with yourself so it&amp;rsquo;s alright to be selfish because you are the only entity reaping any reward from the endeavor.&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;P.S.&lt;/b&gt; All was not lost on my Android development journey. As fate would have it, Google has put out a series of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.udacity.com/courses/android&#34;&gt;free instructional videos&lt;/a&gt; through Udacity on Android development for beginner, intermediate and advanced levels. There is also an accredited course where, upon completion, you earn a Google &amp;ldquo;nanodegree&amp;rdquo; in Android development. The degree course has a monthly tuition. I can say that the free-tier was what I was looking for all along and hopefully later this year I&amp;rsquo;ll pursue the nanodegree option.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>