<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Personal on Bits, Rhymes and Life</title>
    <link>http://blog.nocdib.com/tags/personal/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Personal on Bits, Rhymes and Life</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 22 Nov 2016 21:53:01 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://blog.nocdib.com/tags/personal/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Countdown To My Mid-Thirties</title>
      <link>http://blog.nocdib.com/Countdown-To-My-Mid-Thirties/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Nov 2016 21:53:01 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.nocdib.com/Countdown-To-My-Mid-Thirties/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In about seven weeks I will be turning 35 so on that following day I will be closer to age 40 than I will be to age 30. I have always embraced being young but age 35 marks the official end of all things youthful. That is just my personal perspective and since I&amp;rsquo;ve procrastinated with the nebulous task of &amp;ldquo;getting my act together&amp;rdquo; since I was 18 I feel a certain sense of urgency in doing it now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nothing that I do in the next two months will radically change my status in life (or will it?) but I do have some realistic goals that I would like to reach in that time:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;1) Finish hacking together my work side-project&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
While I can&amp;rsquo;t go into detail about the particulars of this project I can say that it is very doable and that, if nothing else, it would provide me with experience in immersing myself with new technology and devising a final product in relative short order. This project will push my personal project, YB, to a secondary priority but that experience will be applicable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;2) Get stronger and more flexible&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
For the past two weeks I&amp;rsquo;ve been doing isolated yoga stretches to increase flexibility in my hips, shoulders and back. I&amp;rsquo;d like to be more consistent with that, preferably five days a week, and at the same time I would like to start increasing my basic strength with bodyweight exercises like push-ups, abdominal crunches and air squats. I don&amp;rsquo;t have a specific benchmark set but if I see myself being more flexible and able to increase my exercise repetitions then mission accomplished.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;3) Update this blog&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
This blog can use a theme update so I should take a couple of hours and give it a facelift.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;4) Finish reading at least two books&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
It isn&amp;rsquo;t a tall order to finish reading two books in seven weeks but with everything that I do during the day I limit my reading time to only during my work commute. A total of 90 minutes each day is 7.5 hours in a work week. That should be more than enough to finish two books.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that I have my goals specified and a deadline established I should really get and do what needs to be done or deal with the embarrassment of making birthday blog post admitting my shortcomings. So, time to get started.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>