<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Throwback on Bits, Rhymes and Life</title>
    <link>http://blog.nocdib.com/tags/throwback/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Throwback on Bits, Rhymes and Life</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 05 May 2016 02:33:49 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://blog.nocdib.com/tags/throwback/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Throwback Thursday: Cypress Hill - Insane in the Membrane</title>
      <link>http://blog.nocdib.com/Throwback-Thursday-Cypress-Hill-Insane-In-The-Membrane/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 May 2016 02:33:49 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.nocdib.com/Throwback-Thursday-Cypress-Hill-Insane-In-The-Membrane/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/RijB8wnJCN0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
In observance of Cinco de Mayo (Mexican Independence Day) I&amp;rsquo;ll walk down memory lane with the Cypress Hill. Truth be told B-Real is half-Mexican, Sen Dog is Cuban and DJ Muggs is Italian-American but still. The &amp;ldquo;Black Sunday&amp;rdquo; album was one of the first cassette tapes I had ever bought. &amp;ldquo;Insane in the Membrane&amp;rdquo; was the lead single which ended up becoming a hit nationwide. I&amp;rsquo;d say it is still one of the defining Hip-Hop tracks of the 90&amp;rsquo;s among the likes of &amp;ldquo;Baby Got Back&amp;rdquo; by Sir-Mix-A-Lot and &amp;ldquo;Jump Around&amp;rdquo; by House of Pain. &amp;ldquo;I Ain&amp;rsquo;t Going Out Like That&amp;rdquo; was a hard-hitting follow-up track along the lines of &amp;ldquo;Deep Cover.&amp;rdquo; With two strong lead singles Black Sunday definitely made Cypress Hill known on the East Coast but their several subsequent albums never had the same appeal or radio attention. Honestly, I can&amp;rsquo;t say that I have heard Cypress Hill on East Coast radio since Black Sunday. The tracks that I like which came afterwards are ones that I saw music videos for: &amp;ldquo;Tequila Sunrise&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Rap Superstar.&amp;rdquo; Maybe in this era of streaming music I should take the time to catch up on their discography. I&amp;rsquo;ll put that on my to-do list for next week.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Throwback Thursday: Eric B and Rakim - I Aint No Joke</title>
      <link>http://blog.nocdib.com/Throwback-Thursday-Eric-B-and-Rakim-I-Aint-No-Joke/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Apr 2016 08:19:33 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.nocdib.com/Throwback-Thursday-Eric-B-and-Rakim-I-Aint-No-Joke/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/2TN-kDEKxF0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
If you ask a group of true hip-hop fans who the top 5 greatest lyricists of all time are you&amp;rsquo;d likely hear the name Rakim mentioned at least 70% of the time. Your favorite rapper (over the age of 30) probably has him in the top 3. His whole persona embodied the essence of what I remembered 80&amp;rsquo;s New York City hip-hop being but I didn&amp;rsquo;t catch onto him until his first solo album was released in 1997. Prior to that he was part of the eponymous DJ/MC duo Eric B and Rakim but their career spanned from 1987 to 1992, or from when I was between ages 5 and 10. As a kid, the only people around my age who knew of their music learned of them through an older sibling so I didn&amp;rsquo;t acknowledge them until I had gotten much older.&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
I can&amp;rsquo;t recall when exactly was the first time I had heard &amp;ldquo;I Ain&amp;rsquo;t No Joke&amp;rdquo; but I know it was the bass drum and clap pattern that caught me first and then Rakim&amp;rsquo;s braggadocious lyrics. The music video also captured the zeitgeist of NYC at the time with the flat-top haircuts, Fila windbreakers, gold rope chains, rings on all fingers, graffiti murals, etc. If I had to pick one definitive track for hip-hop in the late 80&amp;rsquo;s it would be this one for it&amp;rsquo;s versatility as a party-rocker, a lyrical showcase and a DJ showcase. It&amp;rsquo;s crazy how it&amp;rsquo;s almost 30 years old.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Throwback Thursday: Lin Que - Let it Fall</title>
      <link>http://blog.nocdib.com/Throwback-Thursday-Lin-Que-Let-it-fall/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Mar 2016 06:14:38 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.nocdib.com/Throwback-Thursday-Lin-Que-Let-it-fall/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Thanks to YouTube&amp;rsquo;s autoplay feature this mid-90&amp;rsquo;s gem started playing. In a day where Nicki Minaj is the queen of NYC rap it&amp;rsquo;s nice to take a trip down memory lane to 21 years ago when female emcees were as gritty as the guys. Lin Que was cut from the same cloth as Champ MC, Boss, Nonchalant and Fugees-era Lauryn Hill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly enough, Hype Williams co-directed the video and he is the father of the 90&amp;rsquo;s Hip Hop music video directors. This video shows his signature use of fades between shots but while he&amp;rsquo;s known for his use of vivid color he went for black-an-white this time. Under Sylvia Rhone&amp;rsquo;s guidance Elektra Records was responsible for a number of female acts in 90&amp;rsquo;s urban music. Lin Que wasn&amp;rsquo;t as commercially successful as labelmates like Missy Elliot but she defnitely represented lyrically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/rWF5owcnCrY&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>