<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Bits on Bits, Rhymes and Life</title>
    <link>http://blog.nocdib.com/categories/bits/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Bits on Bits, Rhymes and Life</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 26 Jul 2016 00:47:59 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://blog.nocdib.com/categories/bits/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Making Mobile Moves</title>
      <link>http://blog.nocdib.com/Making_Mobile_Moves/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Jul 2016 00:47:59 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.nocdib.com/Making_Mobile_Moves/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Two months ago I started a new job in the Technology division of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;The New York Times&lt;/a&gt; and I guess I couldn&amp;rsquo;t have started at a better time. Two weeks ago we had Maker&amp;rsquo;s Week, a week-long company &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hackathon&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;hackathon&lt;/a&gt; where people from the Technology, Design, and Product divisions pitched ideas and worked on projects to be presented at the end of the week. I was part of a three-person group led by a product manager on the Search Team who proposed a mobile app that could take a picture of a Times headline and direct the user to the digital version of the article. The idea was born from her experience commuting to NYC on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mta.info/mnr&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Metro-North&lt;/a&gt; train where she noticed newspaper readers taking pictures of article headlines, presumably to share them or to save them for later. I thought it was a good idea to do a quick proof-of-concept in Android with and we were fortunate enough to have an eager intern with lots of free time and some Android programming experience to join the team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our team formed on a Monday and we were set to present on Friday afternoon so time was of the essence for me plus I had other job obligations. The intern was an integral part of the team and really took control of the development while I played a supplemental role. For the technology we used an open source optical character recognition (OCR) library called &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/rmtheis/tess-two&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Tesseract&lt;/a&gt; to read the characters from the words in the image and sent that text to an internal search API which would then return the results in order of relevance. Our goal was to identify the most timely article so we just returned the first result or notified the user that no results were returned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The outcome of our collective effort was successful. Accurate results were returned at a rate of 80% or greater. People were impressed at our presentation and today I had the opportunity to demonstrate the app to higher-ups in the company who are in positions to put the idea in the development pipeline for the flagship Android mobile app. Needless to say I am excited but with the intern soon to return to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.stanford.edu/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Stanford University&lt;/a&gt; I will be the only technical point of contact in the office for the project. This means that I have to become very proficient with Android development rather quickly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Google has &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.udacity.com/course/android-development-for-beginners--ud837&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;some&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.udacity.com/course/developing-android-apps--ud853&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;free&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.udacity.com/course/advanced-android-app-development--ud855&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;videos&lt;/a&gt; via Udacity that I found helpful at the beginner level so I&amp;rsquo;ll continue with them for advanced concepts. Once I&amp;rsquo;m done with those I&amp;rsquo;ll probably begin pursuing the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.udacity.com/course/android-developer-nanodegree-by-google--nd801&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Nanodegree in Android Development&lt;/a&gt;. For now, I cannot divulge more information about the technical aspects of the project since it may soon become company property but I think I will make a general blog post about OCR recognition on Android using Tesseract in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Learning How To Learn Part 2: The First 20 Hours</title>
      <link>http://blog.nocdib.com/Learning-How-To-Learn-Part-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Jun 2016 13:32:10 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.nocdib.com/Learning-How-To-Learn-Part-2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My &lt;a href=&#34;../Learning-How-To-Learn-Part-1/&#34;&gt;first post&lt;/a&gt; on learning how to learn was inspired from watching this video:&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/lB6K60mkmho&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
Josh Kaufman’s words struck a cord with me because he eloquently and concisely summed up in 23 minutes what it took me years to learn. Some of the concepts are still a work-in-progress for me today. Interestingly enough, he mentions that learning computer programming was part of his research into the basic effort necessary to become proficient at something. Becoming a better, more marketable programmer is what continues to motivate me in refining my ability to learn and retain new information while efficiently managing my time. When he distilled the principles into five steps it all made sense relative to my personal experiences.
&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Be specific with your goals&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
The more general your goals are, the more likely you are to lose focus. Success is a journey, the progressive realization of a goal, and every journey is a culmination of a series of steps. When you outline the steps that you will take instead of just focusing on the desired destination you will more efficiently reach your destination without deviating off course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be a good basketball player you have to at least be able to move effectively with the ball and pass it. Depending on the position you play your ball-handling ability needs to be better than other&amp;rsquo;s. In addition to that you may need to be more skilled as a long-range or mid-range shooter than someone who is taller and better built to being near the basket. Similarly, the person near the basket needs to be stronger and more powerful to be an imposing force against defenders in tight spaces. Then you have the defensive aspects that each player needs to focus on as well. When you consider all of these things it becomes evident that simply having the goal of becoming a good basketball player can lead you to go around in circles doing basketball-related activities without focusing on what specifically would make you a good player.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Identify the aggregate components that your goals are comprised of&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
Along the lines of a goal being a series of steps most general skills are a combination of other related skills. With the basketball analogy there are various skills at work to make a good player and each requires its own level of attention. Handling the ball requires practice as does shooting the ball. Sometimes there is overlap and sometimes the skills are isolated but they each require attention. Once you identify these accompanying components you are better able to strategize your approach to the goal step-by-step.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Select the resources that will help you to learn what is necessary to accomplish your goals&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
My first post on this subject focused on this point. Choosing resources is crucial. Garbage input leads to garbage output so evaluate proven material, see which works best with your style of learning and build your knowledge base.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Create an environment conducive to practicing&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
Some people can feel productive working in a bustling coffee shop. Some people prefer studying in the shared quiet space of a library. Other people need personal isolation whether it’s quiet or not. Establish whichever environmental configuration works for you, eliminate distractions and get to work.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Allocate 20 consistent hours to dedicate towards practice&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
If you want to do something well you have to be able to at least dedicate 20 hours to it. Anything less would be a trivial attempt. If you can’t carve out that much time from your schedule to do something then you aren’t in a position to be able to do it well. Consistent hours doesn’t necessarily mean continuous hours so for some things 20 minutes a day may be sufficient whereas two hours a day in the form of two one-hour sessions is needed for others. In either case, daily practice at these levels will result in measurable improvement from when you started. If you practice something for two hours one day a week you most likely be stuck on a metaphorical hamster wheel because your lapses far exceed your efforts. Consistency is the key and the more often you do something the quicker it becomes second nature. The more time you put into doing something, the better the result will be.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>If You Use Vagrant Then You Should Give Otto a Try</title>
      <link>http://blog.nocdib.com/If-you-use-Vagrant-then-you-should-be-using-Otto/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Apr 2016 06:13:52 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.nocdib.com/If-you-use-Vagrant-then-you-should-be-using-Otto/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I was first introduced to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.vagrantup.com/&#34;&gt;Vagrant&lt;/a&gt; while working on a backend development project last year. If you aren&amp;rsquo;t familiar with Vagrant it&amp;rsquo;s basically a configuration wrapper around your preferred virtual machine software that permits you to customize the setup of a VM using a text file called Vagrantfile along with any desired  provisioning files (Chef, Salt, Ansible). Since the configuration is managed with text files it&amp;rsquo;s easy to make changes without manually removing and installing software on the VM and the settings are easily shareable among different users using version control. The alternatives would be to either manually configure a VM and distribute the large image file or to develop the application on individual workstations. With the latter you are bound to encounter the issue of inconsistent behavior due to variances in machine setups among the team. Vagrant is  mature and has been widely adopted by the tech industry, so much so that it spawned &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.hashicorp.com&#34;&gt;a company&lt;/a&gt; that focuses on open source and commercial dev ops software offerings. I&amp;rsquo;m not sure whether it was deliberate or consequential but each of the products after Vagrant were interoperable and formed a suite of distributed systems management solutions. In a clever and resourceful move, Hashicorp combined the VM management of Vagrant with some of their other offerings into a single solution that not only allows you to develop your standalone applications but also to deploy them to the cloud without ever needing to leave your command-line. This all-in-one solution is called &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.hashicorp.com/blog/otto.html&#34;&gt;Otto.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Otto&amp;rsquo;s level of automation is steps beyond what even Vagrant does to the point where it can detect the file types of an existing project and automatically configure a development environment for it. For example, run the &amp;ldquo;otto compile&amp;rdquo; command in a folder with Golang .go source files and you get an environment that already has a Gopath configured to the directory  the command was run from. For building workstation environments Otto leverages Vagrant under the hood. If you only need it for local development then you can use it for just that. Want to deploy your project to Amazon Web Services? Otto will automatically download &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.packer.io/&#34;&gt;Packer&lt;/a&gt; to build your desired image and then use &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.terraform.io&#34;&gt;Terraform&lt;/a&gt; to deploy it without you having to touch the AWS console.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Otto is in the early zero-point version stages so it&amp;rsquo;s probably a good idea to give it some more time before implementing it in a mission-critical production setting. If you are on a small team that can afford to audit new technology then Otto is well worth it. For my personal project use it&amp;rsquo;s more than sufficient so I&amp;rsquo;ve decided to stick with it instead of standalone Vagrant because it&amp;rsquo;s bound to be the full successor by the time it&amp;rsquo;s production certified.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NOTE:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/b&gt; This is an honest and unbiased assessment. I am in no way affiliated with Hashicorp or its employees. I did meet &lt;a href=&#34;http://twitter.com/mitchellh&#34;&gt;Mitchell Hashimoto&lt;/a&gt; once, though.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Learning How To Learn Part 1: Choosing The Proper Resources</title>
      <link>http://blog.nocdib.com/Learning-How-To-Learn-Part-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Apr 2016 13:32:10 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.nocdib.com/Learning-How-To-Learn-Part-1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;For most of my life I had conflated the word &amp;ldquo;learn&amp;rdquo; with the word &amp;ldquo;memorize.&amp;rdquo; Sadly, I think that the American education system is responsible for this because, for as long as I could remember, memorizing information was given precedence over actually understanding what was taught. The only subject that defied this convention was Mathematics which also happened to be the subject I liked the least. The problem with only memorizing atomic facts of information is that while you may be able to recall information accurately enough to get the correct answer on a test you overlook the importance of personally interpreting the information and making connections with other bits of information. The more I work with graph databases (Neo4j in particular) is the more I see the real-life applications of connected information, data.&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
&amp;ldquo;Information&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;data&amp;rdquo; are two more words that are often wrongfully used synonymously but I don&amp;rsquo;t intend to go into detail on commonly misused English words. When it comes to learning I am actually still &lt;i&gt;&lt;u&gt;learning&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/i&gt; how to do it in the best way for myself. I compare it to any skill where there are a core set of basic principles that the individual develops their own personal style from. Right now, I&amp;rsquo;m refining my personal style of learning to achieve the result of gaining understanding, efficiently.&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
Terms like &amp;ldquo;visual learner&amp;rdquo; have crept into the American scholastic vocabulary over the last decade but they didn&amp;rsquo;t exist when I was going to school. I&amp;rsquo;ve come to see that although I can function well with traditional learning methods I actually learn quicker with aided instruction. In other words, I can read material and teach myself something, however, I progress more quickly through visually-aided learning. In an age where streaming online video is pervasive I&amp;rsquo;m sure this style of learning has helped many more folks other than myself. Something about didactic engagement, whether it&amp;rsquo;s real-time or asynchronous, resonates well with me but I realize that the method of teaching is only as effective as the resource conveying the information.&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
Last year I paid for &lt;a href=&#34;https://fedora.bitfountain.io/courses/android&#34;&gt;a self-paced online course&lt;/a&gt; that taught Android development. I had never found a book on the subject that worked well with me nor had I found any of the online tutorials, even ones from Google, helpful past the initial stages. As a result, I had for a long time dismissed Android development as something that was hard to learn and not worth my time. Apple iOS development, on the other hand, had a variety of written resources that were easier for me to understand and become quickly productive with. When I started the Android course it was informative and I thought I was progressing well but several hours into it I came to realize that it had gone from explaining concepts to basically saying &amp;ldquo;enter this code to see this happen.&amp;rdquo; At the beginning I was taking notes but for several of the videos I hadn&amp;rsquo;t taken a single note because I hadn&amp;rsquo;t learned anything. You can tell anyone how to enter some code and run a command to make the computer display &amp;ldquo;hello, world&amp;rdquo; but if you don&amp;rsquo;t explain the mechanics behind what is going on then the student hasn&amp;rsquo;t learned why what they are doing provides the end result. The course, like most resources on computer programming ended up being like this:&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://blog.nocdib.com/blog_images/owl.jpg&#34;&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
Choosing resources that compliment your style of learning is crucial. Not everything will work for everyone. I can&amp;rsquo;t say that the course wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be beneficial to anyone because someone could compensate for the lack of explanation with their own research and gain understanding that way but I simply don&amp;rsquo;t have the time to be presented with information that I have to research just to understand it. I require a resource that explains the what and the why in enough detail so that I can apply it independently and then do any requisite research, if necessary. This is why there are scores of books written on any given subject. Whether it&amp;rsquo;s teaching calculus, basket-weaving, origami, etc. the intention of any instructional text is the same but each one may not work the same way with everyone&amp;rsquo;s style of learning and level of understanding. I used to wonder why many major book stores often include cafes where you could read books before buying them and even had lenient refund policies where you could return a book within a timeframe that you could actually finish reading it. Now I know why. Auditing your resources is important. Committing to anything for the purpose of learning should be treated like an interpersonal relationship but with an inanimate object. When you find something you like you should get to know it and see if it could be right for you. If there is strong potential that it will give you what you need then you could fully commit to it but if it doesn&amp;rsquo;t meet your expectations it&amp;rsquo;s best to end things quickly so as not to waste your time. Ultimately, the relationship you have with learning is one that you have with yourself so it&amp;rsquo;s alright to be selfish because you are the only entity reaping any reward from the endeavor.&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;P.S.&lt;/b&gt; All was not lost on my Android development journey. As fate would have it, Google has put out a series of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.udacity.com/courses/android&#34;&gt;free instructional videos&lt;/a&gt; through Udacity on Android development for beginner, intermediate and advanced levels. There is also an accredited course where, upon completion, you earn a Google &amp;ldquo;nanodegree&amp;rdquo; in Android development. The degree course has a monthly tuition. I can say that the free-tier was what I was looking for all along and hopefully later this year I&amp;rsquo;ll pursue the nanodegree option.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Best Golang Tutorial Around</title>
      <link>http://blog.nocdib.com/The-best-golang-tutorial-around/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Mar 2016 13:21:51 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.nocdib.com/The-best-golang-tutorial-around/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;TL;DR: Read &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.golangbootcamp.com/book&#34; target=&#34;_new&#34;&gt;this tutorial&lt;/a&gt; and watch &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.udemy.com/learn-how-to-code/learn/v4/content&#34; target=&#34;_new&#34;&gt;these videos&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Golang, also known as Go, has been gaining traction in recent years as a mainstream programming language, particularly in the space of web services. At a time when dynamically-typed, interpreted languages like Python and Ruby are dominating that arena while the frameworks that are built with them are handling front-end content or REST API calls I found it interesting that a statically-typed, compiled language had a growing buzz around it. Back in Spring 2012, after I had just ended a job that made heavy use of Erlang I remember my cousin&amp;rsquo;s husband mentioning his interest in learning Go. Having just dealt with a niche language like Erlang&amp;ndash;which I found to be unpleasant&amp;ndash;I wasn&amp;rsquo;t interested in even hearing about another programming language that hadn&amp;rsquo;t been widely adopted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the middle of 2014 &lt;a href=&#34;http://nickmanning.net/&#34; target=&#34;_new&#34;&gt;Nick Manning&lt;/a&gt; started the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/nycgolang/&#34; target=&#34;_new&#34;&gt;Golang NYC meetup group&lt;/a&gt; and I began attending since I already knew him from the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/nycneo4j/&#34; target=&#34;_new&#34;&gt;NYC Neo4j meetup group&lt;/a&gt;. Hearing the testimonials of Go converts piqued my interest but one meeting in particular made me want to try the language for myself. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bjornroche.com/&#34; target=&#34;_new&#34;&gt;Bjorn Roche&lt;/a&gt; gave a presentation about using the &lt;a href=&#34;https://revel.github.io/&#34; target=&#34;_new&#34;&gt;Revel web framework&lt;/a&gt; to power the backend of the mobile app &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.shimmeo.com/&#34; target=&#34;_new&#34;&gt;Shimmeo&lt;/a&gt;. During the presentation he compared Revel to the Java/Scala web framework &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.playframework.com&#34; target=&#34;_new&#34;&gt;Play&lt;/a&gt;. I had a strong interest in Play and was about to use it on my own personal project but after hearing that there was a Go equivalent I was convinced to give Go and Revel a try. Nothing helps you learn a new language better than actually implementing something with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first step was to learn Go. I&amp;rsquo;m pretty particular with my learning materials and I&amp;rsquo;m just not the type who becomes proficient from online documentation and web searches alone. Finding the right introductory material wasn&amp;rsquo;t easy since there was a dearth of tutorials and well-written, published books on Go. I had found one e-book, whose name I will not mention, but I found its explanation and the progression of material to be deficient. By chance I had stumbled upon one of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/user/toddmcleod&#34; target=&#34;_new&#34;&gt;Todd Mcleod&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a&gt; YouTube videos and left a comment. He quickly responded and suggested that I take a look at a new Golang video course that he recently published on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.udemy.com/learn-how-to-code/learn/v4/content&#34; target=&#34;_new&#34;&gt;Udemy&lt;/a&gt;. I bought access to the videos for a nominal fee and it was the best investment in programming-related material that I have ever made. Simply put, if you have prior computer programming experience there is no way that you couldn&amp;rsquo;t become proficient with Go by the end of the course. While doing the course I had also come across Matt Aimonetti&amp;rsquo;s e-book &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.golangbootcamp.com/book&#34; target=&#34;_new&#34;&gt;Go Bootcamp&lt;/a&gt; and noticed that Todd McLeod&amp;rsquo;s course actually elaborated on many of those examples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are interested in learning Go and are looking for a tutorial that blends brevity with comprehensiveness then I suggest reading &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.golangbootcamp.com/book&#34; target=&#34;_new&#34;&gt;Go Bootcamp&lt;/a&gt;. If you need greater depth then look at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.udemy.com/learn-how-to-code/learn/v4/content&#34; target=&#34;_new&#34;&gt;Todd&amp;rsquo;s video course on Udemy&lt;/a&gt;. After tackling the language with these resources I actually found it better to create my own REST API without using a framework. Go is a powerful language that allows you to do just that without a lot of overhead.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Journey Of A Thousand Miles Begins With A Leap</title>
      <link>http://blog.nocdib.com/A-journey-of-a-thousand-miles-begins-with-a-leap/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Feb 2016 20:07:14 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.nocdib.com/A-journey-of-a-thousand-miles-begins-with-a-leap/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It’s been a long time coming (about 6 years) but I’ve finally settled on an idea for a mobile development project to invest my time into. Two years of that time was spent selecting an idea that wasn’t already at least partially implemented, another two years was spent getting acclimated with the tech scene well enough to know which direction to go with it and another two years was was spent dealing with life in general along with general laziness. I&amp;rsquo;ve been gainfully employed for the entire time so it&amp;rsquo;s not as though this project was something that I thought about daily. Now is just the time that I decided to double-down and actually get serious about building something tangible. I have high hopes for my idea so I figured that I will chronicle my progress. If nobody ever reads this it will still be my personal record of the steps I made towards accomplishing something that I&amp;rsquo;ve been dreaming about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All posts related to this project will be prefaced with &amp;ldquo;YB.&amp;rdquo; I don&amp;rsquo;t want to mention specifics about what the app will do but I will say that it is mobile-first, socially-based and has heavy emphasis on geolocation. I will be developing the full stack on my own using technologies that I am learning along the way. Hopefully this will become the resource that I wish I found back in the Summer of 2009 to help me get started. If I could minimize the time needed for someone to undertake their own project then I’d be more than satisfied. While I don’t believe in numerology, astrology or any other form of time/numeric-based omens I can’t help but think that today being &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leap_year#Leap_day&#34;&gt;Leap Day&lt;/a&gt; is psuedo-symbolic since I’m going forward to embark on this personal quest. Well, here goes nothing.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Setting Up A Squid Proxy Using Digital Ocean</title>
      <link>http://blog.nocdib.com/Setting-up-a-Squid-proxy-using-Digital-Ocean/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Aug 2015 09:17:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.nocdib.com/Setting-up-a-Squid-proxy-using-Digital-Ocean/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;With all of the challenges that come with being an American living overseas who has the patience to deal with sites like Google and Wikipedia automatically defaulting to their local versions? Not me. But seriously, I do find it annoying when websites default to their Swedish language versions. I’d also like to be able to watch geographically-specific content such as local American news, Netflix and streaming premium cable programs which aren’t accessible to Internet traffic outside of the United States. I tried using a subscription-based public VPN service but experienced significant lagging while streaming Netflix so I decided that a personal proxy was would be the best option.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.digitalocean.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Digital Ocean&lt;/a&gt; is a cloud-based hosting services that allows customer to create low-cost, high-performing virtual private servers (VPS) in under a minute. These servers (called droplets) can then be accessed via SSH from any terminal and operate no differently than any local instance of Linux or FreeBSD. Routing my Internet traffic through a U.S.-based server would allow me to use the Internet as if I was in the United States without physically being there. Squid is a proxy server for routing Internet traffic and that is exactly what I need. There are several tutorials on how to configure Squid in various manners but many are for previous versions and not the current version, 3, so I thought I’d share how I got it to work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After I created a new droplet based in New York running Ubuntu 14.04 64-bit I installed Squid. All of my set up was done using the root user so I never needed to use the “sudo” command but I’ll include it for those who are not using root.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;nohighlight&#34;&gt;
sudo apt-get install squid
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the installation verify that Squid is running.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;nohighlight&#34;&gt;
initctl list | grep squid3
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should get a response like this (but with a different process id):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;nohighlight&#34;&gt;
squid3 start/running, process 3481
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you don’t see it then manually start Squid and check for the running process again:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;nohighlight&#34;&gt;
sudo start squid3
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now when you verify that Squid is running you should see that it is and the process id associated with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A crucial step in securing the proxy is requiring authentication, a username and password, to access it. I learned this the hard way a few years ago when I set up a proxy without securing it and it was hijacked by spammers to send mass emails in less than 48 hours. First, run the following command to get the necessary package:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;nohighlight&#34;&gt;
apt-get install apache2-utils
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Create a password file. It’s easiest to create it in same folder as the configuration file. Replace [username] with whatever name you desire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;nohighlight&#34;&gt;
htpasswd -c /etc/squid3/passwd [username]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When prompted to, enter your desired password. Then run this command to find the path to the authentication program. Copy this path because you will need it in the next step. You may get more than one result but select the path to an application and not any other type of file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;nohighlight&#34;&gt;
dpkg -L squid3 | grep ncsa_auth
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Open the configuration file &lt;b&gt;/etc/squid3/squid.conf&lt;/b&gt; and add the following near the top of the file:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;nohighlight&#34;&gt;
auth_param basic program [path from previous step] /etc/squid3/passwd
auth_param basic children 5
auth_param basic realm [title for the login window]
auth_param basic credentialsttl 2 hours
auth_param basic casesensitive off
acl ncsa_users proxy_auth REQUIRED
http_access allow ncsa_users
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a nutshell, those lines tell Squid where to find the valid username/password list and that both values are case-insensitve. Then create a user group where authentication is required and only allow users in that group to access the proxy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Somewhere in the file should be a line that looks like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;nohighlight&#34;&gt;
http_port [port_number]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Usually the port number is 3128. You can change this value if you desire but remember it since you will be referencing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These next configuration options are optional so you can use whatever you desire and skip the steps you do not need since your configuration desires may be different than mine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;**** START OPTIONAL SECTION ****&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I needed from my proxy was for it not to cache, not to show my computer’s IP as the true origin and for all traffic to go through the proxy and not directly to me. The following lines do those things, respectively, and are at the end of the file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;nohighlight&#34;&gt;
cache deny all
request_header_access Allow allow all
request_header_access Authorization allow all
request_header_access WWW-Authenticate allow all
request_header_access Proxy-Authorization allow all
request_header_access Proxy-Authenticate allow all
request_header_access Cache-Control allow all
request_header_access Content-Encoding allow all
request_header_access Content-Length allow all
request_header_access Content-Type allow all
request_header_access Date allow all
request_header_access Expires allow all
request_header_access Host allow all
request_header_access If-Modified-Since allow all
request_header_access Last-Modified allow all
request_header_access Location allow all
request_header_access Pragma allow all
request_header_access Accept allow all
request_header_access Accept-Charset allow all
request_header_access Accept-Encoding allow all
request_header_access Accept-Language allow all
request_header_access Content-Language allow all
request_header_access Mime-Version allow all
request_header_access Retry-After allow all
request_header_access Title allow all
request_header_access Connection allow all
request_header_access Cookie allow all
request_header_access Proxy-Connection allow all
request_header_access User-Agent allow all
request_header_access All deny all
forwarded_for off
always_direct deny all
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;**** END OPTIONAL SECTION ****&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With all of the options in place you can test that your proxy works. Save the configuration file and apply the changes to Squid with this command:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;nohighlight&#34;&gt;
squid3 -k reconfigure
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Change the proxy settings in your browser so that all connections are routed through the public IP of your droplet using the port number that you specified in the configuration file. Everything should work as expected. If you have any questions/issues then feel free to reach me in the comments.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>