<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Phife Dawg on Bits, Rhymes and Life</title>
    <link>http://blog.nocdib.com/tags/phife-dawg/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Phife Dawg on Bits, Rhymes and Life</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 24 Mar 2016 19:40:08 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://blog.nocdib.com/tags/phife-dawg/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Throwback Thursday: A Tribe Called - Quest Award Tour</title>
      <link>http://blog.nocdib.com/Throwback-Thursday-A-Tribe-Called-Quest-Award-Tour/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Mar 2016 19:40:08 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.nocdib.com/Throwback-Thursday-A-Tribe-Called-Quest-Award-Tour/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/P800UWoE9xs&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1993 was an interesting year for me musically because I was 11 and it had been about a year since I started taking a personal interest in music. At the end of the prior year Dr. Dre released his classic album The Chronic. Mid-1993 saw Tupac emerge as a bonafide solo artist with &amp;ldquo;I Get A Round&amp;rdquo; and Cypress Hill dropped their classic &amp;ldquo;Insane in the Membrane&amp;rdquo; around the same time. Growing up in New Jersey and gravitating towards West Coast rap while being completely oblivious to the East Coast fixtures seems odd in retrospect but at the time I knew nothing about anything else. November of 1993 had another West Coast classic, Snoop Doggy Dogg&amp;rsquo;s Doggystyle, take the music world by storm but earlier that month A Tribe Called Quest released Midnight Marauders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The day that Midnight Marauders was released, November 9, 1993, was also the day that the Wu Tang Clan released their debut album which captivated me and took the NYC area radio stations by storm. Still, A Tribe Called Quest&amp;rsquo;s lead single &amp;ldquo;Award Tour&amp;rdquo; managed to get some consistent radio play and it was my introduction to the group. The follow-up single &amp;ldquo;Electric Relaxation&amp;rdquo; was sonically pleasing but my hip-hop tastes were in another direction and A Tribe Called Quest became a musical afterthought to me. I recognized their merit but I was never truly a fan. Me being from the East Coast and admitting this is blasphemy to some people but it&amp;rsquo;s the truth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only recently have I gained an interest in listening to earlier music from A Tribe Called Quest and fellow Native Tongues members Leaders of the New School and De La Soul. Sadly, yesterday, I heard that group member Phife Dawg had passed away. I had known for years that he had kidney issues and I&amp;rsquo;m sorry to hear that he succumbed to his ailment. While being soberly reminded about the frailty of our mortal existence I&amp;rsquo;ll use this news as motivation to listen to their entire discography in chronological order. Maybe my more mature listening ear will finally be able to recognize what so many hip-hop fans have already recognized decades ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;R.I.P Malik &amp;ldquo;Phife Dawg&amp;rdquo; Taylor&lt;br/&gt;
November 20, 1970 – March 22, 2016&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>