<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Self Improvement on Bits, Rhymes and Life</title>
    <link>http://blog.nocdib.com/tags/self-improvement/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Self Improvement on Bits, Rhymes and Life</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://blog.nocdib.com/tags/self-improvement/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Learning How To Learn Part 2: The First 20 Hours</title>
      <link>http://blog.nocdib.com/Learning-How-To-Learn-Part-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Jun 2016 13:32:10 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.nocdib.com/Learning-How-To-Learn-Part-2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My &lt;a href=&#34;../Learning-How-To-Learn-Part-1/&#34;&gt;first post&lt;/a&gt; on learning how to learn was inspired from watching this video:&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/lB6K60mkmho&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
Josh Kaufman’s words struck a cord with me because he eloquently and concisely summed up in 23 minutes what it took me years to learn. Some of the concepts are still a work-in-progress for me today. Interestingly enough, he mentions that learning computer programming was part of his research into the basic effort necessary to become proficient at something. Becoming a better, more marketable programmer is what continues to motivate me in refining my ability to learn and retain new information while efficiently managing my time. When he distilled the principles into five steps it all made sense relative to my personal experiences.
&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Be specific with your goals&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
The more general your goals are, the more likely you are to lose focus. Success is a journey, the progressive realization of a goal, and every journey is a culmination of a series of steps. When you outline the steps that you will take instead of just focusing on the desired destination you will more efficiently reach your destination without deviating off course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be a good basketball player you have to at least be able to move effectively with the ball and pass it. Depending on the position you play your ball-handling ability needs to be better than other&amp;rsquo;s. In addition to that you may need to be more skilled as a long-range or mid-range shooter than someone who is taller and better built to being near the basket. Similarly, the person near the basket needs to be stronger and more powerful to be an imposing force against defenders in tight spaces. Then you have the defensive aspects that each player needs to focus on as well. When you consider all of these things it becomes evident that simply having the goal of becoming a good basketball player can lead you to go around in circles doing basketball-related activities without focusing on what specifically would make you a good player.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Identify the aggregate components that your goals are comprised of&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
Along the lines of a goal being a series of steps most general skills are a combination of other related skills. With the basketball analogy there are various skills at work to make a good player and each requires its own level of attention. Handling the ball requires practice as does shooting the ball. Sometimes there is overlap and sometimes the skills are isolated but they each require attention. Once you identify these accompanying components you are better able to strategize your approach to the goal step-by-step.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Select the resources that will help you to learn what is necessary to accomplish your goals&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
My first post on this subject focused on this point. Choosing resources is crucial. Garbage input leads to garbage output so evaluate proven material, see which works best with your style of learning and build your knowledge base.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Create an environment conducive to practicing&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
Some people can feel productive working in a bustling coffee shop. Some people prefer studying in the shared quiet space of a library. Other people need personal isolation whether it’s quiet or not. Establish whichever environmental configuration works for you, eliminate distractions and get to work.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Allocate 20 consistent hours to dedicate towards practice&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
If you want to do something well you have to be able to at least dedicate 20 hours to it. Anything less would be a trivial attempt. If you can’t carve out that much time from your schedule to do something then you aren’t in a position to be able to do it well. Consistent hours doesn’t necessarily mean continuous hours so for some things 20 minutes a day may be sufficient whereas two hours a day in the form of two one-hour sessions is needed for others. In either case, daily practice at these levels will result in measurable improvement from when you started. If you practice something for two hours one day a week you most likely be stuck on a metaphorical hamster wheel because your lapses far exceed your efforts. Consistency is the key and the more often you do something the quicker it becomes second nature. The more time you put into doing something, the better the result will be.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Learning How To Learn Part 1: Choosing The Proper Resources</title>
      <link>http://blog.nocdib.com/Learning-How-To-Learn-Part-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Apr 2016 13:32:10 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.nocdib.com/Learning-How-To-Learn-Part-1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;For most of my life I had conflated the word &amp;ldquo;learn&amp;rdquo; with the word &amp;ldquo;memorize.&amp;rdquo; Sadly, I think that the American education system is responsible for this because, for as long as I could remember, memorizing information was given precedence over actually understanding what was taught. The only subject that defied this convention was Mathematics which also happened to be the subject I liked the least. The problem with only memorizing atomic facts of information is that while you may be able to recall information accurately enough to get the correct answer on a test you overlook the importance of personally interpreting the information and making connections with other bits of information. The more I work with graph databases (Neo4j in particular) is the more I see the real-life applications of connected information, data.&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
&amp;ldquo;Information&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;data&amp;rdquo; are two more words that are often wrongfully used synonymously but I don&amp;rsquo;t intend to go into detail on commonly misused English words. When it comes to learning I am actually still &lt;i&gt;&lt;u&gt;learning&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/i&gt; how to do it in the best way for myself. I compare it to any skill where there are a core set of basic principles that the individual develops their own personal style from. Right now, I&amp;rsquo;m refining my personal style of learning to achieve the result of gaining understanding, efficiently.&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
Terms like &amp;ldquo;visual learner&amp;rdquo; have crept into the American scholastic vocabulary over the last decade but they didn&amp;rsquo;t exist when I was going to school. I&amp;rsquo;ve come to see that although I can function well with traditional learning methods I actually learn quicker with aided instruction. In other words, I can read material and teach myself something, however, I progress more quickly through visually-aided learning. In an age where streaming online video is pervasive I&amp;rsquo;m sure this style of learning has helped many more folks other than myself. Something about didactic engagement, whether it&amp;rsquo;s real-time or asynchronous, resonates well with me but I realize that the method of teaching is only as effective as the resource conveying the information.&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
Last year I paid for &lt;a href=&#34;https://fedora.bitfountain.io/courses/android&#34;&gt;a self-paced online course&lt;/a&gt; that taught Android development. I had never found a book on the subject that worked well with me nor had I found any of the online tutorials, even ones from Google, helpful past the initial stages. As a result, I had for a long time dismissed Android development as something that was hard to learn and not worth my time. Apple iOS development, on the other hand, had a variety of written resources that were easier for me to understand and become quickly productive with. When I started the Android course it was informative and I thought I was progressing well but several hours into it I came to realize that it had gone from explaining concepts to basically saying &amp;ldquo;enter this code to see this happen.&amp;rdquo; At the beginning I was taking notes but for several of the videos I hadn&amp;rsquo;t taken a single note because I hadn&amp;rsquo;t learned anything. You can tell anyone how to enter some code and run a command to make the computer display &amp;ldquo;hello, world&amp;rdquo; but if you don&amp;rsquo;t explain the mechanics behind what is going on then the student hasn&amp;rsquo;t learned why what they are doing provides the end result. The course, like most resources on computer programming ended up being like this:&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://blog.nocdib.com/blog_images/owl.jpg&#34;&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
Choosing resources that compliment your style of learning is crucial. Not everything will work for everyone. I can&amp;rsquo;t say that the course wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be beneficial to anyone because someone could compensate for the lack of explanation with their own research and gain understanding that way but I simply don&amp;rsquo;t have the time to be presented with information that I have to research just to understand it. I require a resource that explains the what and the why in enough detail so that I can apply it independently and then do any requisite research, if necessary. This is why there are scores of books written on any given subject. Whether it&amp;rsquo;s teaching calculus, basket-weaving, origami, etc. the intention of any instructional text is the same but each one may not work the same way with everyone&amp;rsquo;s style of learning and level of understanding. I used to wonder why many major book stores often include cafes where you could read books before buying them and even had lenient refund policies where you could return a book within a timeframe that you could actually finish reading it. Now I know why. Auditing your resources is important. Committing to anything for the purpose of learning should be treated like an interpersonal relationship but with an inanimate object. When you find something you like you should get to know it and see if it could be right for you. If there is strong potential that it will give you what you need then you could fully commit to it but if it doesn&amp;rsquo;t meet your expectations it&amp;rsquo;s best to end things quickly so as not to waste your time. Ultimately, the relationship you have with learning is one that you have with yourself so it&amp;rsquo;s alright to be selfish because you are the only entity reaping any reward from the endeavor.&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;P.S.&lt;/b&gt; All was not lost on my Android development journey. As fate would have it, Google has put out a series of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.udacity.com/courses/android&#34;&gt;free instructional videos&lt;/a&gt; through Udacity on Android development for beginner, intermediate and advanced levels. There is also an accredited course where, upon completion, you earn a Google &amp;ldquo;nanodegree&amp;rdquo; in Android development. The degree course has a monthly tuition. I can say that the free-tier was what I was looking for all along and hopefully later this year I&amp;rsquo;ll pursue the nanodegree option.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>