<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Development on Bits, Rhymes and Life</title>
    <link>http://blog.nocdib.com/categories/development/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Development on Bits, Rhymes and Life</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://blog.nocdib.com/categories/development/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Year 35</title>
      <link>http://blog.nocdib.com/Year_35/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Feb 2017 07:32:18 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.nocdib.com/Year_35/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A few of weeks ago I turned 35. In the weeks leading up to my birthday I had specified some personal goals that I desired to achieve by that &lt;strikethrough&gt;dreaded&lt;/strikethrough&gt; day. Here is how I did:&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;b&gt;1) Finish hacking together my work side-project&lt;/b&gt; &lt;i&gt;(Done!)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
This project is multi-phased and will take months to complete but I was able to complete the initial proof-of-concept by the end of December.&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;b&gt;2) Get stronger and more flexible&lt;/b&gt;&lt;i&gt; (In Progress.)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
I got noticeably stronger since I went from doing push-ups in sets of 10 to doing them in sets of 25. I can&amp;rsquo;t say that I have seen a marked difference in my flexibility but that takes longer to notice.&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;b&gt;3) Update this blog&lt;/b&gt;&lt;i&gt; (Failed!)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
Hugo doesn&amp;rsquo;t have as many available themes as Wordpress or Tumblr but I still cannot decide between the available ones. I&amp;rsquo;ll make myself sit down one Saturday sometime soon and change it.&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;b&gt;4) Finish reading at least two books&lt;/b&gt;&lt;i&gt; (Failed, but&amp;hellip;!)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
I have nothing to blame for this but my own laziness. So many days went by where I got on the bus to work and spent the entire commute on Facebook or lazily sitting half-asleep. What I did manage to do was to finish one book by my birthday and then finish another one at the end of January. This puts me on pace for one of my new year&amp;rsquo;s resolutions: to read one book a month.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>