<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Rakim on Bits, Rhymes and Life</title>
    <link>http://blog.nocdib.com/tags/rakim/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Rakim on Bits, Rhymes and Life</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://blog.nocdib.com/tags/rakim/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Throwback Thursday: Eric B and Rakim - I Aint No Joke</title>
      <link>http://blog.nocdib.com/Throwback-Thursday-Eric-B-and-Rakim-I-Aint-No-Joke/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Apr 2016 08:19:33 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.nocdib.com/Throwback-Thursday-Eric-B-and-Rakim-I-Aint-No-Joke/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/2TN-kDEKxF0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
If you ask a group of true hip-hop fans who the top 5 greatest lyricists of all time are you&amp;rsquo;d likely hear the name Rakim mentioned at least 70% of the time. Your favorite rapper (over the age of 30) probably has him in the top 3. His whole persona embodied the essence of what I remembered 80&amp;rsquo;s New York City hip-hop being but I didn&amp;rsquo;t catch onto him until his first solo album was released in 1997. Prior to that he was part of the eponymous DJ/MC duo Eric B and Rakim but their career spanned from 1987 to 1992, or from when I was between ages 5 and 10. As a kid, the only people around my age who knew of their music learned of them through an older sibling so I didn&amp;rsquo;t acknowledge them until I had gotten much older.&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
I can&amp;rsquo;t recall when exactly was the first time I had heard &amp;ldquo;I Ain&amp;rsquo;t No Joke&amp;rdquo; but I know it was the bass drum and clap pattern that caught me first and then Rakim&amp;rsquo;s braggadocious lyrics. The music video also captured the zeitgeist of NYC at the time with the flat-top haircuts, Fila windbreakers, gold rope chains, rings on all fingers, graffiti murals, etc. If I had to pick one definitive track for hip-hop in the late 80&amp;rsquo;s it would be this one for it&amp;rsquo;s versatility as a party-rocker, a lyrical showcase and a DJ showcase. It&amp;rsquo;s crazy how it&amp;rsquo;s almost 30 years old.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>